CHAPTER 8

Slave Trade and Traffic in Tuticorin
under the Dutch to Colombo,
Cape Town and the Netherlands,
1660-1791

The Dutch East India Company transported both slaves (unfree labourers) and free labourers during the famines in the Tamil country in the years around 1660 to Sri Lanka and Jakarta because the trade in humans was found to be very lucrative. Dutch burghers (free traders) sailed to Tuticorin and they purchased slaves. Prospective native traders also carried many slaves to Colombo in ships which is reported on 2 April 1660.1 The slaves transported were branded with a small company mark (VOC) on the right thigh or arm. Those who arrived were not familiar with the building construction work in Colombo and some died in a year. Many slaves hailing from Thanjavur area were released and allotted land for cultivation. It is reported that more than 900 slaves were employed in cultivating the lands around Colombo by 1662.2

The Dutch factor in Tuticorin was asked to procure slaves during 1670-1. Besides slaves one finds that many free labourers were also purchased and sent to Colombo due to labour shortage there. It is mentioned in Dutch sources that Sinhalese were too lazy and not greatly disposed to fortification works and also to digging the earth and other irrigation related works.3

In 1674 the Dutch Company abolished the use of hired labour in Colombo. Hence the number of hired labourers and coolies from Tuticorin were not transported and their number dwindled.4 Dutch records mention that slaves, coolies, peons and footmen (free and hired servants) were brought from Tuticorin to Colombo to work at the fortifications. This practice was discontinued in 1674.5

It is reported that 1,839 free labourers and also slaves were transported between 1673 and 1677 from the port of Tuticorin and Manapaadu to Sri Lanka. Regulations were modified for slave trade and an order was passed on 2 December 1676, which stated that ships could sail with slaves from Tuticorin to Sri Lanka with only a Dutch sailing permit.6 360 slaves transported to Colombo from Tuticorin in 1678 were transferred to Jakarta followed by another 800 slaves in 1679. It is stated that only slaves employed in the loading and unloading of cargoes in the ships in Colombo were retained.7

The Dutch factory at Colombo in 1681 had 1,993 Tamil slaves and later 1,570 in 1685. The strict control of maritime traffic to Sri Lanka by the Dutch Company acted as counter interest to slave trade. Often the main sources for slaves ran dry and the Dutch Company found not a single slave for purchase in Tuticorin in 1684.8

An ordinance promulgated by the Dutch in 1685 can easily be misunderstood that forbade the import of slaves from Tamil Coast to Sri Lanka.9 Pragmatism ruled and the document itself explains that the Dutch Company dearly needed the slaves. Rules and regulations about slave trade and imports have always been misunderstood in the light of interrelated stakes at the Dutch factories. In 1685 the company prohibited the import of slaves from Malabar and Tuticorin only by the private citizens. The reason was that the Dutch Company itself was the main slave trader.10 An order was passed on 6 December 1685 by the Dutch forbidding those on board the Company ships and private sailing vessels to carry the slaves of the nayak kingdom of Madurai from the port of Tuticorin as the ruler was against slave trade.11 After three years (in 1688) the ban was lifted and slaves were exported from the port of Tuticorin and Manapaadu. Trade in humans continued in 1688, 1689 and 1690.12

The Dutch in Colombo received slaves from Tuticorin and had 1,520 in 1688. Later the number increased to 1,787 by 1694. Incoming workers and slaves reached illegally in ships through private slave traders to Colombo were detected in 1692. They were confiscated and put to work at fortifications in Colombo.13 The Dutch Company had allowed the export of 3,859 slaves by the private merchants from the Tamil Coast to Sri Lanka during 1694-6. In 1695 3,500 slaves were imported to Jaffna and the traders paid the import duties. Hendrick Zwaardecroon the commander of Jaffnapatnam noted that import of more people means more mouths to be fed, while rice was dear rather than labour at the time. He explicitly stated that he would have preferred if traders had brought in rice rather than humans.14 Thus the relationship between rice and slave market is also an interesting line of enquiry.

The Dutch continued to transport slaves to Colombo and had 1,741 in 1697 and 1,582 slaves in 1704.15 The slaves who reached were employed at Galle, Jaffna, Trincomalee and Negombo to meet the labour needs of the Dutch Company. However, the company could not compete with the Dutch private traders in purchasing and transporting slaves from Tuticorin.16 The nayak ruler of Tamil country often opposed slave trade but famines, warfare and crop failure in 1707 had very favourably responded to export of slaves.17

THE TRANSPORT OF SLAVES FROM TUTICORIN
TO CAPE TOWN IN SOUTH AFRICA AND
TO THE NETHERLANDS, 1694-1734

It had become a custom by the Dutch Company higher officials while returning to The Netherlands to take with them their slaves for their personal assistance. Therefore it was ordered that these slaves brought to The Netherlands should be sent back to their respective countries. In 1644 the Dutch Council in Jakarta mentioned that on the orders of the Directors of the Dutch East India Company in Amsterdam, it stated that the Dutch had not been allowed to transport slaves from India to The Netherlands. Slaves if transported would be confiscated without any further judicial process.18 In another ordinance in 1646, the prosecutor of the Court of Justice in Jakarta reminded that the transport of slaves to The Netherlands was punishable by a fine of 50 reals.19 The ordinance of Jakarta in 1646 clearly mentioned that the superiors in The Netherlands were troubled with regard to the return of slaves to India. It was declared that slaves illegally transported from India would be given their freedom. In 1647, it was stipulated that the fine imposed on the transport of slaves had been fixed and increased to 100 reals. The Dutch Company officials complained that the return of slaves to India resulted in high costs. They noted that it was very important to prevent the slave trade to the Netherlands with effective means.20 The high-ranking servants of the Dutch Company had continued to bring their slaves. In 1694, one finds two slaves called Polvist and Victoria had been transported from Tuticorin to Amsterdam by Jacob Pauw who was the owner. It is known that the slave owner had paid the transport cost and provisions for the voyage of these two slaves to the Netherlands.21

It is further reported that four men slaves and a woman slave from Tuticorin were carried in a ship that sailed to The Netherlands during 1695 and 1707. They were sold at Cape Town in South Africa when the ship halted. The profit made by the slave owner on his way back to The Netherlands was very high and attractive.22

The travel ban of slaves from India to Netherlands was just to make it more difficult to bring the slaves to The Netherlands. But these slaves came to be sold in the midway at Cape Town. Further in 1734, the regulations for the transport of slaves to The Netherlands bound voyages were sharpened, by limiting the number of slaves to four persons for every high employee of the Dutch East India Company. While this new practice was introduced one finds more slaves who were men, who were purchased and taken in a ship that sailed and on arrival at Cape Town the slaves were sold. The slave owners received the money on their way to the voyage to The Netherlands.23

THE GROWTH OF SLAVE TRADE OF THE DUTCH
COMPANY FROM TUTICORIN TO SOUTH
AFRICA AND SRI LANKA, 1730-1780

The Dutch in Tuticorin continued to trade in slaves and the company had received many slaves from the region of Cape Comorin (Kanyakumari). These slaves were exported to Colombo and Galle. Some of them were also exported to the Cape Town on ships sailing to The Netherlands. Dutch records mention that 103 slaves (respectively, 23, 24, 15, 21, 18 and 2) from the Tamil Coast were exported to Cape Town between the years 1701, 1703, 1712, 1718, 1736 and 1739.24

Otto Mentzel who lived in Cape Town in 1730s had given a reasonably fair description of the range of Tamil slaves. He stated that the slaves came from Tutegrin (Tuticorin). All these slaves spoke Tamil and belonged to various castes but lived in the Cape Town together without any discrimination.25

The Dutch settlement of Tuticorin became the most important centre of slave shipments to Sri Lanka. Slaves were transported in ships directly from here and, as a result slavery became a way of life in the Tamil-Dutch town, attracting greedy individuals interested in profiting from the commerce in human beings. The native slave agents and merchants were able to supply a substantial number of Tamil slaves from the hinterland of Tuticorin. The Dutch settlement also had a large permanent slave population. There was continuous interaction among different groups of people interested in exporting slaves. The Dutch were compelled to take the assistance of the local agents to obtain slaves because they neither knew the local language nor the places from where they could acquire slaves for export. There were already many dealers conversant with the purchase and sale of the slaves in the inland. Dutch Company officials and servants approached such brokers for supply, who extended active support and cooperation. Dutch Company records mention that slaves for export in the ports were easily available only during the famine years because the natives sold themselves or their children in bondage because of debt and to escape starvation, though the Dutch Company needed a supply of slaves annually. Many slave dealers emerged in Tuticorin owing to the busy trade and one of the famous and the most reputed agent was called Chidambaram. He was paid large sums of money as much as 1,300 pagodas in one year by the Dutch Company for his supply of slaves.26

Dutch privateers in Sri Lanka continued to purchase many slaves who were transported from Tuticorin in the eighteenth century. The company also had a large slave population but they were owned by it. Slave trade and slave ownership in Tuticorin and the letters to and from Tuticorin point out the illicit trade during 1742-3.27 One finds two declarations concerning the ownership of Wouter Gilles Trek of two Tamil female slaves. It was drawn up by Arnoldus Lunel in Tuticorin with deeds of purchase of the slaves in 1775-6. The ownership of Pieter Lambert Trek, the bookkeeper of the Dutch company at Kanyakumari, a Tamil female slave is also found and it was drawn by Arnoldus Lunel in Tuticorin in 1776. The declaration of Pieter Lambert Trek concerning sale of a female slave and her son to Johan Henridk Smith was drawn in Tuticorin in 1776. The ownership of Johannes Martinus Fruins residing at Kanyakumari as a Tamil female slave was drawn by Arnoldus Lunel in Tuticorin in 1780. Thus in the Dutch records one finds plenty of deeds of sale and purchase of the slaves from Tutcorin.28

MANUMISSION OF TUTICORIN SLAVES
IN COLOMBO, 1739-1791

Manumission of slaves by self purchase was not a civil right under the Dutch Company. However, purchase was a route to manumission of Tamil slaves of Tuticorin used by both Dutch Company owned and privately owned slaves in Colombo. Numerous manumissions for exchange of a slave had been recorded. A deed in 1739 refers to the company-owned slaves Petchiammaal and Elammal who were manumitted in exchange for two other slaves called Pasqual and Coridon.29 It should be noted that the enslaved women had provided male slaves to take their place. Kittuammal, another slave was manumitted through a deed dated 13 January 1751. She got manumitted because she supplied her master with Rosetta, another female slave given in bondage in exchange.30 Kittuammal, Petchiammaal and Elammal the slaves were freed by exchange of slaves between 1739 and 1752.

Slaves paid money for manumission to their owners too. During 1750 and 1752 the amount had varied from small to large sums. Kandan and his two children Victoria and Domingo were freed in June 1750 after paying 225 rix dollars. The manumission of two other male slaves called Adriaan and Muthu Karuppan was paid and their freed status had cost 100 rix dollars each. Four slaves (two men and two women) were freed for 50 rix dollars each. Further, Maria and her six children were manumitted for a sum that averaged out to 36 rix dollars per person.31 All the slave owners demanded the full replacement value of their slave considering that the administrative cost of manumitting a slave which was very high including payment to the church which was 10 rix dollars. It is likely that the sum received by slave owners was intended only to cover the administrative costs.

Philippus Matteus Trekels the slave owner of Achilles was paid an enormous sum of 250 rix dollars in 1779.32 Adriana Elisabeth Luders received 30 rix dollars for the manumission of her slave called Cardoes in 1791.33 Variation in price thus depended perhaps on a number of factors, including the slave’s age, level of skill, and relationship with slave owner. The sum paid for manumission by purchase was surely set by the slave owner. A generous master could have been more open to the idea of a slave buying himself out of bondage and so he had set a very reasonable price.

Kasthuri and her daughter Thavasi the slaves were together manumitted for 138 rix dollars. One finds their freed status from Manuel Adam Fernando the slave owner on 20 February 1786.34 Wilhelmina Elisabeth Schreuder manumitted her slave Deepa in March 1786. Deepa had paid the value of herself. The exact amount is not mentioned in the record.35 No clear pattern emerges from some records regarding the differences in the value of male and female slaves.

It is interesting to observe the bewijs (emancipation deeds of slaves) that prove the fact that they preceded the owner’s renunciation of rights over the slave. It thus leads to the conclusion that it was a legal necessity to prove the rightful ownership of a slave before being able to renounce those rights through manumission. To prove that the individual emancipating the slave was the legal owner, he had to present the details of which—the clerks’ names, the date and place where the emancipation deeds had been signed—all that were then noted in the records. Geetha a Tamil slave was freed in 1751 when she presented Rosetta to become a slave in her place in Colombo. The deed points to the fact that Geetha was a privately owned slave. Another example of Dutch Company owned slaves being manumitted in exchange for others took place in March 1739.

In one record, one finds the deed signed at Negombo in Sri Lanka in 1696. But the slave was freed after 56 years, i.e. only in the year 1752. Eight deeds of emancipation of Tamil slaves included references to the certificates signed in Tuticorin. Johanna Obrack, the widow of Pieter de Moor, the kapitein militair (military captain) freed the male slave named Alexander in 1750. The certificate proved that Johanna Obrack was Alexander’s legal owner and signed in Tuticorin in 1724. In this case he served as a slave for 26 years.36 Three other slaves belonging to Michiel Symans who were freed in 1781 also had the certificates signed in Tuticorin in 1724. In this case the slaves had served for 57 years.37 These evidences prove that the slaves were mainly children when picked up and transported from Tuticorin to Sri Lanka. Dutch records from 1774 to 1781 mention the ships that annually sailed from Tuticorin to Colombo and Galle carrying slaves and there was a large scale slave migration.38

The death of Tamil slaves from Tuticorin in Sri Lanka between 1771 and 1775 had been recorded. In Colombo, between March and August 1771 ten Company slaves died and seven of them were recorded as Tamils from Tuticorin.39 The following year, between March and June a total of eight slaves died, and four of them had been transported from Tuticorin.40 The list from December 1775 had been the longest, enumerating 19 deaths between March and August of that year.41 The nine slaves named in the list were transported through Tuticorin. In four cases the slave was listed as the son or daughter of a transported slave.

SLAVERY IN TUTICORIN: THE DOMESTIC
SLAVES AND THEIR PATHETIC
LIVES, 1681-1746

Slaves were purchased at Tuticorin and the Portuguese artillery men on the west coast in Cochin had employed them in their houses. The dynamics of slave mobility and control had been noticed dealing with interactions that took place in a market. In early April 1681, Sangu the slave named Anthonij (Antony), of 14 years owned by Emmanuel Pereira, the taupas (artillery men) had walked through the bazaar located outside the city of Cochin. He was sent by his master to sell a number of goods.42 While in the market, he was approached by Pedro, who had himself been a slave earlier but ran away several years ago. Pedro had asked Antony whether he wanted to go back to Kallikulam near Tuticorin his birthplace. Antony replied that he did not. Pedro persisted, by asking him time and again whether he wanted to go anywhere else. Antony replied that he was interested in going and visiting the city of Calicut. He further added that though he was interested he could not do so. Pedro agreed to bring a boat near the house of Emmanuel Pereira, his master, on the following Friday. Finally, on Sunday Pedro moored his boat near Emmanuel Pereira’s house and Antony climbed aboard. Just as Pedro was about to sail away, Antony jumped back ashore and told Pedro that he had forgotten to take some of his belongings from the house. He went into the house but, much to Pedro’s surprise (instead of the Antony returning), Pereira came running with weapons drawn, yelling ‘thief’.43 Two nearby taupas men heard Pereira’s voice and they rushed to help while Pedro tried to sail quickly away. But the three jumped into a boat nearby and caught him up while Pedro drew his sword and shield but was quickly overwhelmed by the three pursuers. A quick blow hit his shield, another hit him on the arm, and the last blow made him throw his weapon overboard and surrender. This event happened because Pereira had told Antony sometime ago that if anyone ever tried to tempt him to run away, he should agree to go and immediately tell Pereira, in order to capture that person as a slave thief.44 It is thus known that Antony the slave had a relatively high degree of mobility. Emmanuel Pereira his owner, trusted him and often sent him to the bazaar to engage in economic transactions.

Pedro Gomez the Christian Mukkuvar owned a tavern at Puththanthurai in 1746. He ran the business by employing his slave called Cruz who went early in the morning everyday to open the tavern and he remained there the whole day until its closure in the evening. Cruz was mainly responsible for the daily running of the tavern. On a Sunday evening, Paandi a native of Tuticorin aged 20 called Anthonij (Antony) came to the tavern. He noticed that Cruz the slave was sad. When he asked the reason, Cruz cried bitterly revealing that his master Pedro Gomez had informed that he would sell Cruz to the sailors.45 Antony at that time had suggested that if Cruz came with him he would help him reach his native place. Cruz replied that he did not know his native place. He agreed to leave with Antony if he would really find where the place was.46 Cruz who lived in a hut close to the house of his master Pedro Gomez and his wife Dominga, left Puththanthurai along with Antony that night. Pedro Gomez the owner of the slave was taken aback next day when the doors and windows of the tavern were closed.47 Pedro was informed at that time by some children from the neighbourhood that they had seen Cruz and Antony talking near the water tank the previous night. Pedro immediately realized that he had threatened his slave on Sunday that he would sell him to some sailors and this had probably prompted Cruz to run away.48 According to records, Cruz was eventually found by Pedro Gomez’s relatives near Travancore. They urged him to return to his owner, which Cruz also apparently did and narrated the details.49

EXPORT OF SLAVES CONTINUED FROM
TUTICORIN TO SRI LANKA AS GLEANED
FROM THE REGISTER OF SALES, 1755-1791

Slaves were purchased from Malabar and Canara by the Dutch Company in Cochin. The purchase and sale deeds were prepared and sailing permits were issued by the Dutch authorities for export from Tuticorin. This practice had continued from 1755 to 1791.

The slaves including men and women, were purchased mainly from different places including Purakkadu in Malabar and Vengurla in Canara. These sale and purchase deeds were drafted in Cochin by the Dutch officials. The mention of castes such as Nair, Izhlava, Paraiyar, etc., were noted down. Sometimes professions like lascar, smith, etc., were also mentioned. The age of the slaves had been noted with the minimum of 16 years and maximum of 22 years. After completing the sale formalities in Cochin within ten days, the certificates for transportation were prepared for transporting them to Tuticorin. The records of 1774 as found at the Tamil Nadu State Archives in Egmore, Chennai are badly damaged. There is a separate register containing sailing permits issued for slave transportation in thonies (boats) from Tuticorin to Colombo in Sri Lanka. However, it has been found that very bad and sad things had happened as gleaned from the Dutch records preserved in the National Archives in the Hague, the Netherlands. One finds during the acts of transport with the mention of the old name of the slave, new name of the slave given, caste, gender and the age. One finds Krishnan aged 19 was renamed September. Another slave Krishnan 20 years of age, was renamed Augustus (August). Sankarappan aged 16, was now called Meij (May). Another young man Sankarappan aged 20 was renamed Maart (March). Kittu the slave aged 19, was renamed Junij (June) and Kandan the slave aged 19 was renamed October. Thus the Dutch Company had completely erased the identity of slaves before transporting them from Tuticorin to Sri Lanka.51

TABLE 8.1: SLAVES TRANSPORTED FROM THE PORT
OF TUTICORIN TO SRI LANKA, 1755-1791

Period | Number of slaves
25 January 1755–5 August 1756 | 53
1758 | 145
1759 | 181
1770 | 92
1771 | 189
1772 | 71
1 October 1773–31 December 1773 | 59
5 January 1774–5 June 1774 | 150
1 April 1775-27 June 1775 | 72
3 January 1776–30 April 1776 | 96
19 July 1777–16 December 1777 | 107
1784–1785 | 67
1786 | 88
12 February 1787–20 August 1787 | 99
1 September 1789–27 November 1789 | 114
1790–1791 | 127
TOTAL | 1,710

Source: See Note.50

MADHAN, THE TAMIL SLAVE AND HIS
TRAVEL FROM TUTICORIN TO THE
NETHERLANDS, 1739-1741

An individual labelled as ‘slave’, a young boy, is described as being of Tamil (Malabar) origin. He had been purchased on 1 June 1739 by Christian Dober an employee of the Dutch East India Company at Tuticorin.52 The boy was at that time twelve years old.53 He was abducted from his father which had been stated.54 The village he originally hailed from is unknown. He was taken away from his father and sold off as a slave at the urban centre of Tuticorin. The village did not formally fall under the authority of the Dutch Company in Tuticorin. Hence the village chiefs could not ask the Dutch Company to return the slave boy, even if they came to know about the abduction. Thus abductions normally happened in villages lying outside the Dutch jurisdiction and the slaves were brought for sale to the port. The document certifying the sale gives his name as Maden (Madhan) of the Sanas (Shanar) caste.

Christian Dober kept the slave for domestic purposes for two years in Tuticorin. Later he sailed from Tuticorin to the Netherlands in 1741 and took Madhan the slave with him. Dober had renamed the slave boy Felix. The slave was under his custody in his house even in the Netherlands.

THE TRAVEL OF THE SLAVE FROM THE
NETHERLANDS TO GERMANY, 1741

Christian Dober wanted to join the Moravian Church and live with the Moravian community in Germany. The Moravian missionary movement was founded by Count Zinzendorf, a Lutheran missionary in 1722 at Herrnhut (the Lord’s Watch), near Dresden in Saxony. Zinzendorf offered a part of his estate as a refuge for a group of persecuted believers from Bohemia and Moravia. From these Brethren came the first organized Protestant mission. Zinzendorf became the leader of the Church of the United Brethren (Moravians) and he launched a mission in 1732 to convert the slaves in the Danish islands in the West Indies.

It is gleaned from the diary of David Nitschman a Moravian missionary in 1741 that Christian Dober had promised the young boy Madhan/Felix as a gift to the Moravian community.55 It is unclear from the record whether the boy was brought with the intention of handing over to the Moravian Brethren when he joined the mission or he had actually gifted the slave boy to Zinzendorf.

THE CONVERSION AND BAPTISM OF
THE SLAVE IN GERMANY, 1746

According to Dutch records Madhan/Felix was introduced to the Moravians in S’Heerendiek by Christian Dober after arriving in the Netherlands on 20 July 1742.56 Christian Dober took the slave with him to Germany. The slave boy was baptized by Zinzendorf on 10 January 1746 in Marienborn. His baptismal name was Samuel Johannes. Johan Jacob Sutor another Moravian missionary had reported and confirmed the news that the slave boy of Christian Dober was baptized and called Samuel Johannes.57

Countess Erdmuthe Dorothea, the wife of missionary Zinzendorf had mentioned that Christian Dober had given the slave boy to her immediately after arrival in Marienborn. Christian Dober who got admitted into the Moravian missionary community did so to enhance his reputation with the church leaders. Countess Zinzendorf kept the boy in her house and took care of him. When her husband left for British North America to expand his missionary work she sent him to an orphanage.58

THE SLAVE AND HIS STUDIES IN THE
SEMINARY AT BARBY, 1746-1753

Countess Zinzendorf sent the slave boy to children’s home in Marienborn.59 Samuel Johannes was formally admitted into the Moravian community in 1746. According to archival records he received training as a tailor and later attended the seminary in Barby (Salzlandkreis district).60

SAMUEL JOHANNES AT HERRNHUT:
THE RUNAWAY SLAVE, MARCH 1754

Samuel Johannes was ordered suddenly in March 1754 to come to the town of Herrnhut (Gorlitz district). The reason behind this had been traced. The authorities in the seminary had found growing dissatisfaction with the conduct of the young boy.61 Samuel Johannes was therefore placed in the service of Baron von Schell in Herrnhut on 13 March 1754. The slave boy fled from there after staying fourteen days. Hence a report of absconding was filed. The Berthelsdorf seigniorial court when approached immediately ordered his apprehension on 27 March 1754.62

On the first leg of his flight, Samuel Johannes found refuge on the nearby estate Unwürde of Chamberlain Karl Gotthelf von Hund and Altengrotkau, an active freemason. The Moravian search parties learnt about the place of stay of the slave and they asked the slave to be handed over. Karl Gotthelf von Hund at that time refused to hand over the slave. Countess Zinzendorf sent a letter to Karl Gotthelf von Hund on hearing the news and requested the slave to be returned to her.63

This letter contains many interesting details. One finds the concepts of societal hierarchy and servitude in condensed form. Its terminology hints uncertainty regarding the legal status of Madhan/Felix/Samuel Johannes. The Countess and the Berthelsdorf seigniorial court confirmed and noted that the absconded slave was not a free person. In the very first sentence of the letter one finds mention about the slave’s origin. It designated him as a runaway black Malabar. It further added that the slave was a born slave who had been gifted to the Countess. The letter attempts to assert the fundamental right of her claim of dependence and servitude of the slave.

The letter also affirmed how Christian Dober consigned the boy to Countess Zinzendorf’s care and free disposition. It also proceeds to justify her authority over the runaway black Malabar through the obligations she assumed as a Christian and patron. This is further emphasized by detailing the amount of money she had spent on the slave, on the Christian baptism, education and training of the wild slave. In short, it stated that she had done everything as master, parent, and guardian could do for a serf and ward.

The position of the Countess and the runaway had been construed on two separate levels, one as mistress and slave/ serf with an obligation of obedience and deference. Again it has been said that that the relationship was that of guardian and ward expecting an obligation of loyalty and gratitude. Therefore, the Countess expressed the sole right besides God to claim possession and usage of Samuel Johannes. The slave on the other hand, was not a free man since he was a true born serf to the Countess and as such was bound to remain in subservience until he received a letter of release.64

THE SURRENDER AND ARREST OF SAMUEL
JOHANNES AT BARBY, MAY 1754

After remaining hidden for two months, on the estates of Chamberlain von Hund, Samuel Johannes made his way to Barby in April 1754 and he surrendered himself. An order to keep him under arrest was issued on 4 May 1754 on behalf of Countess Zinzendorf to the court at Barby.65 One finds that Samuel Johannes was eventually transported from Barby to Herrnhut based on legal provisions.66

SAMUEL JOHANNES TRANSPORTED FROM
GERMANY TO PENNSYLVANIA IN BRITISH
NORTH AMERICA AND HIS DEATH, 1754-1763

Within a few months Samuel Johannes was transported in a ship to the town of Bethlehem in Pennsylvania. He was found again with the Moravians. Several enslaved Africans were employed at that time in Bethlehem. There is no information as to whether he was considered a slave or not. By crossing the Atlantic, he had entered a colonial slaving zone where slavery was widespread and obvious. Samuel Johannes was not designated a slave in the Bethlehem records. Also he was not labelled a Negro the term used to refer to slaves in the colonies. Instead, he is repeatedly referenced as a Malabar.67

It is found that Samuel Johannes married Magdalena Mingo, a free woman of African creole and Danish ancestry who had lived in Marienborn and Herrnhut for several years. The marriage took place at the church in a Holy Mass. This ceremony was held along with thirteen other married couples who were all Europeans.68 Samuel Johannes spent nine years till the remainder of his life. He passed away on 24 May 1763.69

The case of Madhan/Felix/Samuel Johannes is especially striking because he was sold by slave owners ending up in Pennsylvania. The name had changed when was sold from one person to another, creating a new identity in the minds of his owners. One finds slavery changing from a dormant state into an actively invoked claim of legal proprietorship, thereby fraying into several categories and partly overlapping categories of dependency. The story of the slave reports say how Moravian missionaries in Europe and in North America had appreciated an opportunity to make slaves become Christians with evangelistic fervour. One also finds that individuals and Moravian community in Germany had slaves with rights of propriety. Community members claimed authority over Samuel Johannes going beyond church discipline, domestic servitude, or serfdom. In sum, slavery had been one of the major undercurrents integrating the histories of the world from the port of Tuticorin on the Tamil Coast to Europe and America. It highlighted the local contexts of the systems of bondage, as well as the long-distance connections forged by the commercialized circuits of slavery and slave trade carried out widely by both the non-Europeans and Europeans.

It may be said that the slaves were transported overseas by the Dutch Company and the trade continued and flourished during famines, droughts and failure of crops. Many of them were very poor and had no means for livelihood except selling themselves voluntarily. There were many native agents, dealers and brokers who helped the Dutch in the procurement and sale of slaves. The labour scarcity in the various Dutch settlements like Jakarta, Colombo, Galle and Cape Town was the main reason for the thriving slave transportation from the port of Tuticorin.

NOTES

1. Nationaal Archief (hereafter NA), Den Haag, VOC 1233, fls. 157-68.

2. NA, VOC 1234, fls. 25r-v; Sri Lanka National Archives (hereafter SLNA), 2712, Colombo Diary, fl. 57.

3. W. Ph. Coolhas, ed., Generale Missiven van de Gouverneurs-Generaal en Raden Aan Heren XII der Verenigde Ossitindische Compagnie, 9 vols., S’ Gravenhage, 1960-84 (hereafter GM), vol. III, p. 793 (31 January 1672).

4. SLNA, 1/20, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, fl. 27v-28 (29 October 1674), fls.35r-36 (3-26 November 1674).

5. SLNA, 1/20, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, fl. 27v-28, fls.35v-36.

6. L. Hovy, Ceylonees Plakkaatboek: Plakkaten en Andere Wetten Uitgevaardigd door het Nederlandse Bestuur op Ceylon, 1638-1796, 2 vols., Hilversum, Verloren, 1991, vol. I, pp. 129, 196-7.

7. SLNA, 1/24, Minutes of the Governor and Council in Colombo, fl. 61v-62; GM, vol. IV, pp. 294, 354.

8. NA, VOC 1396, fl.66v (4 July 1684).

9. L. Hovy, Ceylonees Plakkaatboek, vol. 1, p. 227, Plakkaat 163.

10. Ibid., pp. 1227-8 (6 December 1685).

11. Ibid., pp. 117-8.

12. NA, VOC 1479, fls. 611r-627v.

13. NA, VOC 1506, fls. 1604-5 (31 May 1692).

14. Sophia Pieters, trs., Memoir of Hendrick Zwaardecroon, Commandeur of Jaffnapatam, 1697, Colombo, 1911.

15. Knaap Gerrit, ‘Europeans, Mestizos and Slaves: The Population of Colombo at the end of the Seventeenth Century’, trans. Robert Ross, Itinerario, vol. V, 1981, pp. 84-101, see p. 96.

16. Markus Vink, ‘The World’s Oldest Trade: Dutch Slavery and Slave Trade in the Indian Ocean in the Seventeenth Century’, Journal of World History, vol. 14, no. 2, June 2003, pp. 131-46, see pp. 142-3.

17. GM, vol. VI, p. 496 (30 November 1707).

18. J.A. Van der Chijs, Nederlandsch-Indisch Plakaatboek, 17 vols., Batavia/ S’Gravenhage, 1885-1900, vol. II, p. 88.

19. Ibid., pp. 109-110.

20. Ibid., p. 118.

21. Nationaal Archief, The Netherlands, The Hague (hereafter NL–HaNa), Archief van de VOC, 1540, fls. 363-64.

22. Nigel Worden, ‘Indian Ocean Slaves in Cape Town, 1695-1805’, Journal of South African Studies, 42(3), 2016, pp. 389-408, see p. 406.

23. Nigel Worden, Indian Ocean Slaves, p. 406.

24. NA, VOC 1628, VOC 1630, VOC 1641, VOC 1651, VOC 1653, VOC 2419, VOC 2360, VOC 3843, VOC 7534 and VOC 7538.

25. O. Mentzel, A Complete and Authentic Geographical and Topographical Description of the Famous and (All Things Considered) Remarkable African Cape of Good Hope, Cape Town, Van Riebeeck Society, 1925, vol. II, p. 125.

26. P.M. Markus Vink, ‘The World’s Oldest Trade: Dutch Slavery and Slave Trade in the Indian Ocean in the Seventeenth Century’, Journal of World History, vol. 14, no. 2, June 2003, pp. 131-77, see, p. 146.

27. Tamil Nadu State Archives (hereafter TNSA), Chennai, Cochin Records, no. 352.

28. Lennart Bes, Plaatsingslijst van de Collectie van de familie prins–1656-Zost eeuw, 2003, vol. II, p. 466, see document no. 50, 51, 52, 53.

29. SLNA, Protocols of Deeds of Emancipation of Slaves, 1/4145, VOC, fls.18r-19r (16 March 1739).

30. SLNA, 1/4145, fls. 337v-338r (13 January 1751).

31. SLNA, 1/4146, unpaginated.

32. SLNA, 1/4146 (5 September 1779).

33. SLNA, 1/4146 (5 January 1791).

34. SLNA, 1/4146 (20 February 1786).

35. SLNA, 1/4146 (22 March 1786).

36. SLNA, 1/4145, 1738-52, fls. 332r–v (31 August 1750).

37. SLNA, 1/4146, 1770-95 (24 October 1781), (24 October 1781), (9 December 1786), (9 September 1787).

38. NA, VOC 3402, fls. 516-20 (1774); VOC 3432 fls. 547-51 (1775); VOC 3457, fls. 463-4 (1776); VOC 3485, fls. 528-31 (1777); VOC 3516, fls. 523-7 (1778); VOC 3572, fls. 505-10 (1779-81).

39. NA, VOC 3324, Resoluties, 11 October 1771.

40. NA, VOC 3350, Resoluties, 15 September 1772.

41. NA, VOC 3433, Resoluties, 29 December 1775.

42. NL–HaNa, Nederlandse bezittingen India: Digitale duplicaten Chennai, 1.11.06.11, 66, Scan 75, Case ID Database CR-66-11.

43. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 66, Scan 67, Case ID Database CR-66-11.

44. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 66, Scan 75, Case ID Database CR-66-11.

45. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, inv. no. 440, ff.1–39, Case ID Database CR-440-6; NL-HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 21; NL-HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 37.

46. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 20.

47. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 20; 31-2.

48. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 32.

49. NL–HaNa, 1.11.06.11, 440, fl. 33; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Tuticorin and its Trade with Asia, Africa and Europe, 1570-1880: Colonial Transformation, Human Migration and Interrelations, Puducherry, 2022, pp. 134-5.

50. TNSA, Cochin Records, no. 584, sale and transfer of slaves from 25 January 1755 to 5 August 1756; no. 622, sale and transfer of slaves in 1758; no. 632, sale and transfer of slaves in 1759; no. 886, sale and transfer of slaves in 1770; no. 896, sale and transfer of slaves in 1770-1; no. 925, sale and transfer of slaves in 1772; no. 957, sale and transfer of slaves, from 1 October to 31 December 1773; no. 979, sale and transfer of slaves from 5 January 1774 to 5 June 1774; no. 1003, sale and transfer of slaves from 1 April 1775 to 27 June 1775; no. 1034, sale and transfer of slaves from 3 January 1776 to 30 April 1776; no. 1062, deeds of sale and transfer of slaves from 19 July 1777 to 16 December 1777; no. 1145, permits to export slaves from 18 February 1780 to 29 December 1787; no. 1225, sale and transfer of slaves in 1784 and 1785; no. 1266, sale and transfer of slaves in 1786; no. 1288, sale and transfer of slaves from 12 February to 20 August 1787; no. 1341, sale and transfer of slaves from 1 September 1789 to 27 November 1789; no. 1369, deeds of sale and transfer of slaves in 1790-1.

51. NA, Akten van Transport, VOC, 1.11.06.11, Inventory number 1062.

52. Unitats Archive (hereafter UA), Herrnhut, R.21.A.28.47, See the certificate of sale of the slave boy Maden to Christian Dober, 1 June 1739.

53. Moravian Archives, Bethlehem (hereafter MAB), Pennsylvania, USA, Diary of the Bethlehem congregation, vol. XXVI, 1763-4, pp. 93-5.

54. Alexander Volck, Das entdeckte Geheimniss der Bosheit der Herrnhutischen Secte zu Errettung vieler unschuldigen Seelen, in sechs Gesprächen dargelegt, Frankfurt, Heinrich Ludwig Brönner, 1750, p. 561.

55. UA, R.15.S.2, Diary of David Nitschmann’s (the Syndic) and August Christian Friedrich Ellert’s journey to Ceylon, vol. II, 17 August 1740- 24 November 1741.

56. NA, VOC, 6035, fol. 31.

57. Paul Peucker, ‘Aus allen Nationen: Nichteuropäer in den deutschen Brüdergemeinden des 18. Jahrhunderts’, Unitas Fratrum, vol. 59/ 60, 2007, pp. 1-35, see p. 33.

58. UA, R.6.a.A.74.4, Erdmuthe Dorothea von Zinzendorf to Chamberlain von Hund at Unwürde, 27 March 1754.

59. UA, R.8.33.b.3, The Diary of Wetterau, 2 August 1742; UA, R.4.B.V.b.3.8., Catalog Lindheim, 1744.

60. UA, R.27.291.13, The Register of Seminarians, Barby, 1750.

61. Paul Peucker, ‘Aus allen Nationen’, p. 21.

62. UA, R.6.a.A.74.4, The requisition for the apprehension of a Black Malabar named Samuel Johannes, 27 March 1754.

63. UA, R.6.a.A.74.4, Erdmuthe Dorothea von Zinzendorf to Chamberlain von Hund at Unwürde, 27 March 1754.

64. Ibid.

65. UA, R.6.a.A.74, Order by Siegmund August von Gersdorf on behalf of Countess Zinzendorf, Herrnhut, 4 May 1754.

66. UA, R.6.a.A.74, Pro nota regarding the extradition request from 11 May 1754; UA, R.6.a. A. 74, Passport by the bailiff of Barby, 18 May 1754.

67. MAB, Diary of the Bethlehem congregation, vol. XXVI, fl. 93.

68. MAB, Diary of the Bethlehem congregation, vol. XVII, 20 April 1757, fls. 99-01.

69. MAB, Diary of the Bethlehem congregation, vol. XXVI, fls. 93-5; MAB, ChReg 11, Bethlehem church register, 24 May 1763.